Guide to the Theodore Roosevelt collection, 1883-1953
Roosevelt, Theodore collection
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Theodore Roosevelt collection, 1883-1953 (bulk 1883-1918)
4652
Theodore Roosevelt 1858-1919.
0.5 linear ft.
Correspondence, photographs
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Consists mainly of letters by Roosevelt to a variety of correspondents, but also includes several autographs, photographs, one printed item, and two documents.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
American politician and author, U.S. President from 1901-1908.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Consists mainly of letters by Roosevelt to a variety of correspondents, but also includes several autographs, photographs, one printed item, and two documents. Letters span Roosevelt's career, briefly documenting his activities as governor of New York, Civil Service Commissioner, Commissioner of the New York City Police, Assistant Secretary of the U.S. Navy, Vice President, President, and, in his political retirement, editor in turn at The Outlook and Metropolitan magazines and the Kansas City Star newspaper. Correspondence deals with the handling of internal American political affairs, including dealings with Civil War veterans and a governors' conference on U.S. natural resources; letters to editors concerning books and articles Roosevelt was publishing or being asked to write; and a few letters on religious matters, including a substantial letter on the U.S. government's position vis-à-vis Catholic affairs in the Philippines.
Photographs show Roosevelt and a companion on an excursion in rocky country; and a set of proofs for color postcards documents scenes from Roosevelt's trip to Africa (1910). With the proofs are a contract for printing the images as postcards, an advertisement for the postcard set, and a cover letter from the printer for the proofs. The printed item is an inspirational message Roosevelt wrote for U.S. troops in 1917; the document is a Thanksgiving Day proclamation issued by Roosevelt in 1899 as Governor of New York. Also included in the collection is correspondence between W.J. Crawford and Robert William Glenroie Vail concerning the building of the collection.
Also, Roosevelt's reading copy of a speech delivered at the Ithaca Hotel on October 24, 1910, typed with handwritten corrections in pencil. The speech both attacks trusts and discusses the 1910 New York gubernatorial race between Democrat John Alden Dix and Republican Henry L. Stimson. Also, five photographs of Roosevelt at the Ithaca Hotel; and a photograph of Roosevelt in Albany in 1883, with Assemblyman O'Neil of Franklin County, Assemblyman Isaac L. Hunt of Jefferson County, George Spinney of the New York Times, and Assemblyman Walter Howe of New York.
Also includes a replica of the original Teddy bear.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Roosevelt, Theodore, 1858-1919.; Crawford, W. J.; Roosevelt, Theodore, 1858-1919.; Vail, R. W. G. (Robert William Glenroie), 1890-1966.
Subjects:
Church and state -- United States.; Authors and publishers -- United States.; Big game hunting -- Africa -- Pictorial works.; Picture postcards.; Picture postcards.
Places:
United States-- Politics and government -- 1897-1901.; United States -- Politics and government -- 1901-1909.; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865 -- Veterans.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
NOTES
Large collection of books by and about Roosevelt is also held in the repository.
CONTAINER LIST
- Photographs, Articles, and Speech
  - Photo of two men leading horses across a rocky outcropping. The man in the front appears to be Theodore Roosevelt (3 prints) (Box 1)
  - Photo of two men leading horses across a rocky outcropping. The man in the front appears to be Theodore Roosevelt (large print) (Box 1)
  - Photo of Roosevelt in Albany in 1883, with Assemblyman O'Neil of Franklin County, Assemblyman Isaac L. Hunt of Jefferson County, George Spinney of the New York Times, and Assemblyman Walter Howe of New York (5 x 7" print) (Box 1)
  - Article in the Thursday, February 5, 1953 New York Times Newspaper advertising the restoration of Roosevelt's home on Sagamore Hill (Box 1)
  - Summary of the Roosevelt Collection housed in the Cornell Rare Books and Manuscripts Library (Box 1)
  - Typescript of speech given by Roosevelt in Ithaca, New York, along with photographs of the event., October 24, 1910 (Box 66)
  - Rochester Democrat and Chronicle newspaper showing post election day coverage of the Roosevelt win., November 9, 1904 (Folder 1)
  - Four-color proofs for postcards produced from photographs of Roosevelt's trip to Africa, mainly showing scenes of big game hunting., 1910 (Box 17)
- Correspondence
  - Recipient: W. J. Crawford Junior, September 23, 1926 (Box 1, Folder Rooseveltiana; Letters to W. J. Crawford, Jr.)
    Sender: William Roosevelt
  - Recipient: W. J. Crawford Junior, November 17, 1926 (Box 1, Folder Rooseveltiana; Letters to W. J. Crawford, Jr.)
  - Recipient: Unknown, October 25, 1883 (Box 1, Folder ALS)
    Sender: Theodore Roosevelt
  - Recipient: Mr. Bryan, April 30, 1880 (Box 1, Folder ALS)
  - Recipient: William George Pellew, March 12, 1889 (Box 1, Folder ALS)
  - Recipient: William Potts, December 10, 1889 (Box 1, Folder TLS)
  - Recipient: L. P. Putnam, January 21, 1890 (Box 1, Folder ALS)
  - Recipient: Brander, November 21, 1892 (Box 1, Folder ANoteS)
  - Recipient: H. K. Carroll, August 7, 1895 (Box 1, Folder TNoteS)
  - Recipient: Joshua W. Caldwell, October 9, 1895 (Box 1, Folder TLS)
  - Recipient: T. A. Church, April 8, 1897 (Box 1, Folder TNoteS)
  - Recipient: W. H. Tolman, April 8, 1897 (Box 1, Folder TNS)
  - Recipient: Laurence J. Hodes, September 30, 1897 (Box 1, Folder TNoteS)
  - Recipient: C. S. Devoy, November 24, 1897 (Box 1, Folder TNoteS)
  - Recipient: National Press Bureau, January 17, 1898 (Box 1, Folder TNoteS)
  - Recipient: D. McN. Stauffer, January 20, 1898 (Box 1, Folder TNoteS)
  - Recipient: Robert Underwood Johnson, February 11, 1898 (Box 1, Folder TNoteS)
  - Recipient: J.N. Smith, February 17, 1898 (Box 1, Folder TLS)
  - Recipient: Kurtz Eppley, May 3, 1898 (Box 1, Folder TNS)
  - Recipient: James W. Clarke, August 28, 1898 (Box 1, Folder ANOTES amanuensis)
  - Recipient: J. N. Smith, October 31, 1989 (Box 1, Folder TLS)
  - Recipient: D. C. Heath, December 19, 1898 (Box 1, Folder TNoteS)
  - Recipient: George M. S. Bose, January 13, 1899 (Box 1, Folder TLS)
  - Recipient: Unknown, April 19, 1899 (Box 1, Folder TNoteS)
  - Recipient: D. Turner, November 13, 1899 (Box 1, Folder TNoteS)
  - Recipient: Gen. Horatio C. King, February 3, 1900 (Box 1, Folder TL)
  - Recipient: Gen. Edgar Daniel Sickles, February 5, 1900 (Box 1, Folder TLS)
  - Recipient: Ge. Horatio C. King, February 6, 1900 (Box 1, Folder TL)
  - Recipient: Gen. Horatio C. King, February 7, 1900 (Box 1, Folder TLS)
    Roosevelt expresses regret that H.C. King will be resigning
  - Recipient: William H. Rideing, February 12, 1900 (Box 1, Folder TNS)
  - Recipient: David B. SIckles, November 10, 1900 (Box 1, Folder TNoteS)
  - Recipient: William H. Rideing, December 20, 1900 (Box 1, Folder TNoteS)
  - Recipient: Edward Cary, February 28, 1901 (Box 1, Folder TNoteS)
  - Recipient: Fred J. Hutchinson, May 6, 1901 (Box 1, Folder TLS)
  - Recipient: Annie Nathan Meyer, June 3, 1901 (Box 1, Folder TLS)
  - Recipient: Major John Crane, July 31, 1901 (Box 1, Folder TLS)
    The letter details Roosevelt's thoughts on the issue of removing Catholic friars from the Philippine Islands
  - Recipient: William H. Moody, September 10, 1902 (Box 1, Folder TLS)
  - Recipient: Benjamin Franklin Tracy, September 9, 1903 (Box 1, Folder TLS)
  - Recipient: Mrs. Johnson, January 3, 1904 (Box 1, Folder ALS)
  - Recipient: M. Frederic Mistral, December 15, 1904 (Box 1, Folder TLS)
  - Recipient: Seymour Eaton, January 4, 1906 (Box 1, Folder TLS)
  - Recipient: Christine Walton Dunlap, February 12, 1906 (Box 1, Folder TLS)
  - Recipient: R. W. Gilder, April 6, 1906 (Box 1, Folder TLS)
  - Recipient: Davis, May 12, 1906 (Box 1, Folder Facsimile)
  - Recipient: Robert Bridges, November 10, 1907 (Box 1, Folder TLS)
  - Recipient: Henry A. Buchtel, November 11, 1907 (Box 1, Folder TLS)
    Roosevelt discusses the conservation of the Nation's natural resources
  - Recipient: Gen. Horatio C. King, February 2, 1908 (Box 1, Folder TNoteS)
  - Recipient: John R. Mott, October 12, 1908 (Box 1, Folder Printed L)
    A letter from President Roosevelt regarding the need for more men of ability to lead the aggressive forces of Christianity
  - Recipient: DeB. Randolph Keim, June 27, 1910 (Box 1, Folder TNoteS)
  - Recipient: Robert Underwood Johnson, July 8, 1910 (Box 1, Folder TLS)
  - Recipient: Mr. Jarrett, November 15, 1910 (Box 1, Folder TNoteS)
  - Recipient: James Carleton Young, December 9, 1910 (Box 1, Folder TNoteS)
  - Recipient: Edgar Solomon Shumway, December 23, 1910 (Box 1, Folder TNoteS)
  - Recipient: Charles A. Kofoid, February 2, 1911 (Box 1, Folder TLS)
    Letter discussing a pamphlet on birds. Roosevelt disagrees with the explanation of why crows have only one dark coloring and no "protective variation"
  - Recipient: Robert Bridges, August 22, 1911 (Box 1, Folder TLS)
  - Recipient: George Parsons, April 16, 1912 (Box 1, Folder TNoteS)
  - Recipient: P. S. Ridsdale, February 21, 1913 (Box 1, Folder TLS)
  - Recipient: Charles R. Huntington, May 7, 1913 (Box 1, Folder TNoteS)
  - Recipient: R. M. Johnson, June 26, 1913 (Box 1, Folder TLS)
  - Recipient: W. E. Davenport, September 4, 1913 (Box 1, Folder TLS)
  - Recipient: R. M. Johnson, September 15, 1913 (Box 1, Folder TNS)
  - Recipient: R. M. Johnson, March 18, 1915 (Box 1, Folder TLS)
  - Recipient: Jobiska Johnson, November 29, 1915 (Box 1, Folder TNoteS)
  - Recipient: Mac N. Miller, February 1, 1916 (Box 1, Folder TNoteS)
  - Recipient: Darwin C. Pavey, April 23, 1916 (Box 1, Folder TNoteS)
  - Recipient: Johnston, July 14, 1916 (Box 1, Folder ANoteS)
  - Recipient: Jobiska Johnson, August 24, 1916 (Box 1, Folder ALS)
  - Recipient: To the troops, June 5, 1917 (Box 1, Folder Printed L)
    The teachings of the New Testament
  - Recipient: Warren Barbour, November 26, 1917 (Box 1, Folder TLS)
  - Recipient: Jobiska Johnson, April 1, 1918 (Box 1, Folder ANoteS)
  - Recipient: Earl H. Emmons, June 1, 1918 (Box 1, Folder TNoteS)
  - Recipient: Alfred Meyer, December 23, 1918 (Box 1, Folder TNoteS)
  - Recipient: Unknown (Box 1, Folder Letters (Duplicate photocopies))
    Contains photocopies of all letters
  - Recipient: Unknown, April 6, 1910 (Box 17, Folder Letter (Duplicate photocopy))
    Sender: S. Barchak, The Cushman Company, Springfield, Mass.
    Cover letter for proofs of postcards on Roosevelt's trip to Africa. With this are the proofs, plus 2 copies of a contract between Barchak and The Phelps Publishing Company to print the postcards (contract dated June 4, 1910).
  - Recipient: W. J. Crawford, Junior, April 28, 1924 (Box 1, Folder Rooseveltiana; Letters to W. J. Crawford, Jr.)
    Sender: John Clark
  - Recipient: George Coffin, July 31, 1956 (Box 1, Folder Rooseveltiana; Letters to George Coffin)
    Sender: W. J. Crawford, Junior
  - Recipient: Unknown (Box 1, Folder Rooseveltiana)
    Lists of the holdings of the Crawford Roosevelt Collection
  - Recipient: W. J. Crawford, Junior (Box 1, Folder Rooseveltiana; Letters to W. J. Crawford, Jr.)
    Sender: Willard I. Emerson
    A thank-you letter to the Crawford's for the gift of the Roosevelt Collection
  - Recipient: W. J. Crawford, Junior, October 21, 1926 (Box 1, Folder Rooseveltiana; Letters to W. J. Crawford, Jr.)
    Sender: James R. Garfield
  - Recipient: W. J. Crawford, Junior, February 7, 1955 (Box 1, Folder Rooseveltiana; Letters to W. J. Crawford, Jr.)
    Sender: Dean W. Malott
  - Recipient: W. J. Crawford, Junior, April 11, 1961 (Box 1, Folder Rooseveltiana; Letters to W. J. Crawford, Jr.)
    Sender: Cornelius Van S. Roosevelt
    Discusses a $20 gold coin given to the Smithsonian Institution by C.V.S. Roosevelt
  - Recipient: Dr. Leonard Carmichael, April 10, 1961 (Box 1, Folder Rooseveltiana; Letters to W. J. Crawford, Jr.)
    Letter to the Smithsonian from C. V. S. Roosevelt
  - Recipient: W. J. Crawford, Junior, December 14, 1923 (Box 1, Folder Rooseveltiana: Letters)
    Sender: Robert William Glenroie Vail
  - Recipient: Unknown (Box 1, Folder Rooseveltiana: Letters)
  - Recipient: W. J. Crawford, Junior, December 17, 1921 (Box 1, Folder Rooseveltiana: Letters)
  - Recipient: W. J. Crawford, Junior, January 10, 1922 (Box 1, Folder Rooseveltiana: Letters)
  - Recipient: W. J. Crawford, Junior, December 14, 1922 (Box 1, Folder Rooseveltiana: Letters)
  - Recipient: W. J. Crawford, Junior, January 10, 1923 (Box 1, Folder Rooseveltiana: Letters)
  - Recipient: W. J. Crawford, Junior, January 10, 1923 (Box 1, Folder Rooseveltiana: Letters)
  - Recipient: W. J. Crawford, Junior, March 2, 1923 (Box 1, Folder Rooseveltiana: Letters)
  - Recipient: W. J. Crawford, Junior, April 16, 1923 (Box 1, Folder Rooseveltiana: Letters)
  - Recipient: W. J. Crawford, Junior, May 16, 1923 (Box 1, Folder Rooseveltiana: Letters)
  - Recipient: W. J. Crawford, Junior, July 13, 1923 (Box 1, Folder Rooseveltiana: Letters)
  - Recipient: W. J. Crawford, Junior, December 7, 1923 (Box 1, Folder Rooseveltiana: Letters)
  - Recipient: W. J. Crawford, Junior, December 7, 1923 (Box 1, Folder Rooseveltiana: Letters)
  - Recipient: W. J. Crawford, Junior, December 29, 1923 (Box 1, Folder Rooseveltiana: Letters)
    Thank you from the Trustees of the Roosevelt Memorial Association for the gift of two original cartoons of Roosevelt
  - Recipient: W. J. Crawford, Junior, January 18, 1924 (Box 1, Folder Rooseveltiana: Letters)
  - Recipient: W. J. Crawford, Junior, April 2, 1924 (Box 1, Folder Rooseveltiana: Letters)
  - Recipient: W. J. Crawford, Junior, April 2, 1924 (Box 1, Folder Rooseveltiana: Letters)
  - Recipient: W. J. Crawford, Junior, April 23, 1924 (Box 1, Folder Rooseveltiana: Letters)
  - Recipient: W. J. Crawford, Junior, June 9, 1924 (Box 1, Folder Rooseveltiana: Letters)
  - Recipient: W. J. Crawford, Junior, July 9, 1924 (Box 1, Folder Rooseveltiana: Letters)
  - Recipient: W. J. Crawford, Junior, July 27, 1925 (Box 1, Folder Rooseveltiana: Letters)
  - Recipient: W. J. Crawford, Junior, October 29, 1924 (Box 1, Folder Rooseveltiana: Letters)
  - Recipient: W. J. Crawford, Junior, March 17, 1925 (Box 1, Folder Rooseveltiana: Letters)
  - Recipient: Unknown (Box 1, Folder Rooseveltiana: Letters)
    Image of Roosevelt Bust
  - Recipient: W. J. Crawford, Junior, April 14, 1925 (Box 1, Folder Rooseveltiana: Letters)
  - Recipient: W. J. Crawford, Junior, April 30, 1925 (Box 1, Folder Rooseveltiana: Letters)
  - Recipient: W. J. Crawford, Junior, June 26, 1925 (Box 1, Folder Rooseveltiana: Letters)
  - Recipient: W. J. Crawford, Junior, July 8, 1925 (Box 1, Folder Rooseveltiana: Letters)
  - Recipient: W. J. Crawford, Junior, July 15, 1925 (Box 1, Folder Rooseveltiana: Letters)
  - Recipient: W. J. Crawford, Junior, November 10, 1925 (Box 1, Folder Rooseveltiana: Letters)
  - Recipient: W. J. Crawford, Junior, November 15, 1952 (Box 1, Folder Rooseveltiana: Letters)
  - Recipient: W. J. Crawford, Junior, December 3, 1952 (Box 1, Folder Rooseveltiana: Letters)
  - Recipient: W. J. Crawford, Junior (Box 1, Folder Rooseveltiana: Letters)
    List of Roosevelt material mentioned in the 12/3/1952 letter (4 pages)
  - Recipient: W. J. Crawford, Junior, May 16, 1953 (Box 1, Folder Rooseveltiana: Letters)
  - Recipient: W. J. Crawford, Junior, May 16, 1953 (Box 1, Folder Rooseveltiana: Letters)
    Negative copy of 5/16/1953 letter discussing an appraisal
- Miscellaneous letter fragments and autograph cards
  - Letter, Card #62 (Box 1, Folder ANS)
  - Autograph Card #63 (Box 1, Folder Autographs)
  - Autograph Card #64 Printed on card: Sagamore Hill (Box 1, Folder Autographs)
  - Autograph Card #65 Printed on card: White House, Washington (Box 1, Folder Autohgraphs)
  - Letter Fragment #66 Letter to The Right Honorable Lord Curzon (Box 1, Folder Fragments)
  - Letter Fragment #67 Letter to Reverend Dr. Frank K. Sanders (Box 1, Folder Fragments)
  - Letter Fragment #68 Fragment of a letter discussing Socialism in America (Box 1, Folder Fragments)
  - Letter Fragment #69 Letter of apology (Box 1, Folder Fragments)
- Steiff "Teddy" bear, Knopf im Ohr (button in its ear). (Box 2)